Guide to the G. Evelyn Hutchinson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
G. Evelyn Hutchinson papers
1875-1992
1922-1991
MS 649
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
47.75
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, addresses, notes and research materials, subject files, memorabilia, and photographs relating to G. Evelyn Hutchinson's work as a zoologist and limnologist. The papers highlight his years on the faculty at Yale University but also document his student days at Cambridge University and his early career in South Africa. Of note are materials from his travels as part of the Yale North India Expedition. The collection includes personal papers relating to various members of the Hutchinson family.
Hutchinson, G. Evelyn (George Evelyn), 1903-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of G. Evelyn Hutchinson, 1950s-1990; Robert Cook, 1983 and 1990; the estate of G. Evelyn Hutchinson, 1991-1992; Yvette H. Edmondson, 1992; Nancy Slack, 1997 and 2009; and Dorothea and Francis Hutchinson, 1998; and transferred from Kline Science Library, 1991 and 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is available for research. Some correspondence with Robert H. MacArthur is restricted until 2035.
Associated Materials
G. Evelyn Hutchinson Papers Relating to Rebecca West. General Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biographical / Historical
George Evelyn Hutchinson was born in Cambridge, England, on January 30, 1903. His father, Arthur Hutchinson, was a mineralogist and master of Pembroke College at Cambridge University. Hutchinson's early education was at St. Faith's School, Cambridge, and Gresham's School, Holt. He demonstrated an early interest in natural history, particularly butterflies and aquatic insects, and published his first piece of scholarship when he was fifteen.
Hutchinson was a member of Emmanuel College as an undergraduate and received a B.A. from Cambridge University in 1924. After graduation he spent a year as a Rockefeller Fellow at the Stazione Zoologica in Naples where he studied octopus, squid, and other deep sea animals of Messina but also became fascinated with folklore and art. In 1926 Hutchinson accepted his first academic job as a senior lecturer in zoology at the University of the Witwatersrand in South Africa, where he began his studies of the physical, biological, chemical, and meteorological conditions of lakes of the western Transvaal. In 1928, he married Grace Pickford.
In that same year, Hutchinson made his final career move, joining the faculty of Yale University as an instructor. He rose to become Sterling Professor of Zoology, a post he held until his retirement in 1971. In 1932, Hutchinson was given the opportunity to study the ecosystems of the lakes on the high plateaus of Tibet, as the biologist accompanying the Yale North India Expedition. Hutchinson chronicled his impressions and experiences in The Clear Mirror (1936). On the return trip from India, he met Margaret Seal, who became his second wife in 1933.
Hutchinson is best known for his work in limnology, the study of freshwaters, particularly lakes. Early on he recognized the significance of ecology, and much of his research and writing dealt with the relationship between living organisms and their environment. He was particularly interested in the determining influence of the physical and chemical environment on the ecology of rivers and lakes. In 1935, he demonstrated the importance of horizontal movements of water in stratified lakes in mixing the upper and lower layers of water. In other studies he showed the circulation of phosphorous in stratified lakes and conducted research on the chemistry of lake sediments. In 1957, he published the first volume of his A Treatise on Limnology, a work of such extensive and thorough analysis that it comprised four volumes, the last of which was released posthumously.
Hutchinson had vast theoretical insight and defended the importance of theory as a stimulus to empirical research. In his desire to find order in the diversity of nature, he maintained that there was a need for dialogue between mathematicians and biologists and he employed mathematical models to arrive at general principles. His curiosity and ability to pose stimulating questions on ecological principles inspired his students, many of whom became leading figures in ecology. He asked, and partially answered the question, "Why are there so many kinds of animals?" and he provided a theoretical understanding of how an organism fits in nature, giving a modern definition of the ecological niche. A prolific writer, Hutchinson presented some of his most provocative ideas in his "Marginalia" column in American Scientist.
Hutchinson was an active participant in numerous professional organizations and learned societies. He was a charter member of the Limnological Society of America and its president from 1947 to1948. Elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1950, he served on its Committee on Science and Public Policy and was a foreign member of the Royal Society. He received several honorary degrees, and his contributions were recognized by, among others, the Naumann Medal of the International Association of Theoretical and Applied Limnology (1959), the Frederick Garner Cottrell Award for Environmental Quality of the National Academy of Sciences (1974), the Daniel Giraud Elliot Medal of the National Academy of Sciences (1984), and the Kyoto Prize in Basic Science (1986).
Hutchinson is remembered as a shy, reserved man, with an insatiable curiosity about all fields of human inquiry and a delightful sense of humor. His wife Margaret had died in 1983, and he had married Anne Twitty in 1985. After her death in 1990, Hutchinson, in failing health, had returned to England. He died there on May 17, 1991.
Scope and Contents
The G. Evelyn Hutchinson Papers are a large, yet incomplete, record of the personal life and professional career of a giant in the field of limnology. The papers attest to Hutchinson's long and inspirational career as a scholar and teacher, who shaped the development of the emerging field of ecology. Moreover they demonstrate his broad interests from the Abraxas butterfly and water striders in the insect world, the sexual behavior of birds, and mathematical modeling, to British stamps, medieval art, Guernsey archaeology, ancient inscriptions on Tibetan rocks, and the art and architecture of India and Goa.
While there is material, including correspondence, writings, and photographs, from Hutchinson's youth in England through his tenure at Yale, the bulk of the collection dates from the years following his retirement in 1971. Hutchinson continued to be intellectually active in these years, producing the third and fourth volumes of A Treatise on Limnology and "Marginalia" columns. Both the correspondence and the writings series contain material on these endeavors.
Included in the papers are letters from the most prominent academicians in ecology as well as materials for professional societies in their fledgling years. The large number of files for students, colleagues, and organizations attests to his impact on the field. A supportive mentor, the papers document Hutchinson's continuing role in furthering the careers of his students, both men and women, and his interest in their scholarly pursuits. The papers do not include materials such as course syllabi or lecture notes from Hutchinson's teaching, but there is some documentation relating to the Yale science curriculum.
The papers include copious files concerning Hutchinson's publications and speeches, most notably his A Treatise on Limnology. It is, however, difficult to trace the progress of Hutchinson's inquiry and observation on the condition of lakes or the variation in animal species from the relatively limited amount and disorderly state of research data retained by him. Perhaps the best documented of his scholarly endeavors is his work on the Yale North India Expedition in 1932. Letters to his parents and to Grace Pickford, from this period, abound with detail, and every other series in the papers contains some material from this exploration. Hutchinson was a member of the Episcopal Church, and some of his correspondence and writings he explore perceived conflicts between science and religion. In his later writings, he also examines the depiction of nature in art.
The papers include personal materials, but in selecting materials to make available for research, Hutchinson made a deliberate effort to protect his privacy and that of others. There is little in the papers, for instance, concerning his marriages. In preparing to write of his early years and development, a work that would become The Kindly Fruits of the Earth, Hutchinson amassed materials on his parents and their families along with his letters and memorabilia from his student days and travels. These materials provide insight into the milieu which gave rise to Hutchinson's intellectual curiosity about the world.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and two additions: I. Correspondence, 1904-1991. II. Topical Files, 1927-1992. III. Research and Writings, 1922-1991. IV. Personal Files, 1916-1991. V. Photographs, 1875-1991.
American scientist; Abraxas; Biogeochemistry; Biology -- Study and teaching; Ecology; Guano; Lakes; Limnology; Niche (Ecology); Population biology; Goa, Daman and Diu (India); India -- Description and travel; Anderson, Myrdene, 1934-; Deevey, Edward S. (Edward Smith), 1914-1988; Edmondson, W. T. (Walles Thomas), 1916-2000; Edmondson, Yvette H.; Ellsworth, Phoebe; Fersman, A. E. (Aleksandr Evgenʹevich), 1883-1945; Garber, Marjorie B., 1944-; Hutchinson, G. Evelyn (George Evelyn), 1903-1991; Lovejoy, Thomas E.; MacArthur, Robert H.; Margulis, Lynn, 1938-2011; McConnell, R. A. (Robert A.); Oved, Yemaiel; Patrick, Ruth; Pickford, Grace E., 1902-1986; Ripley, S. Dillon (Sidney Dillon), 1913-2001; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia; American Society of Limnology and Oceanography; Ecological Society of America; International Association of Theoretical and Applied Limnology; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.). Committee on Science and Public Policy; University of Cambridge -- Students; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale North India expedition, -- 1932-1933
- Correspondence, 1904-1991; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is composed of both incoming and outgoing exchanges with correspondents who include some of the most eminent scholars both in the United States and around the globe, as well as family and personal friends. The correspondence files also document the organization and development of numerous professional organizations and their work as spokesmen to the public. The series is arranged alphabetically by the personal or corporate name of the correspondent.
  The bulk of the correspondence dates after 1940, but there are a few letters dating from Hutchinson's years at Cambridge and in South Africa. While not obviously lacking correspondence for any particular year, the series bulks larger for the period after Hutchinson's retirement in 1971. While one would expect a larger quantity of material from the period of Hutchinson's active teaching career, by comparison with the post retirement period, the letters from the 1940s through the 1960s seem diminished, as if Hutchinson had either saved less during these years or had lost or weeded files at some later date.
  Reviewing the names of Hutchinson's correspondents begins to suggest the size of his intellectual network and the variety of his interests. Not surprisingly many of them are in biology and other fields related to ecology and because of his education and research interests, several are from England and Italy: Enrico Bonati, Paul Colinvaux, Paul Ehrlich, Clyde Goulden, Arthur Hassler, Julian Huxley, David Lack, Luigi Provalosi, Vittorio and Livia Tonolli. There is also correspondence with Russian colleagues G. F. Gauze and Nicholai Formozov, as well as exchanges with Yale colleagues Leo Buss, John Buettner Janusch, Raymond Lindeman, Donald Poulson, and George Vernadsky. R. A. McConnell's correspondence describes his work on ESP and parapsychology and his attempts to publish it for a scholarly audience. Hutchinson shared comradery and intellectual challenges with a number of women, including Ruth Patrick, Lynn Margulis, Phoebe Ellsworth, Mary Gritten, Donna Haraway, Penelope Jenkin, Sharon Kingsland, Lorraine Larison, Estella Leopold, Margaret Mead, Sharon Ohlhorst, Miriam Rothschild, and Marjorie Garber.
  Some of Hutchinson's major correspondents are former graduate students, many of whom became leading figures in ecology. The correspondence documents the important influence Hutchinson had in their development, and the files for R. J. Benoit, Vaughn Bowen, John L. Brooks, Alan Covich, Edward Deevey, W. Thomas Edmondson, Thomas Goreau, Louis Hutchins, Thomas Lovejoy, Robert MacArthur, Howard Odum, Gordon Riley, Lawrence Slobodkin, and J. R. Vallentyne may include comments on their work, suggestions for further development of their ideas, references for jobs, and other professional concerns, as well as personal messages concerning family and travel. In his post retirement years, the files include correspondence about manuscripts on which Hutchinson advised or worked cooperatively with several associates and students, including Ursula Cowgill, Myrdene Anderson, Karen Porter Glaus, Alison Jolly, Eleanora Robbins, and Saran Twombly. There is also a considerable amount of correspondence with Yvette Edmondson concerning the publication of the fourth volume of A Treatise on Limnology.
  Hutchinson took a leading role in organizations such as the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, the American Society of Limnology and Oceanography, the Conservation Foundation, the International Association of Theoretical and Applied Limnology, and the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, and files for each of them document this activity. The files for the National Academy of Sciences are particularly large, attesting to Hutchinson's work on awards committees, the Environmental Studies Board, nominating committees, and the Reports Review Committee, the latter concerning debate over the appropriate position to take on the effects of herbicide use in Vietnam. There is also significant correspondence concerning the nation's natural history museums, including the Smithsonian and the American Museum of Natural History in New York. The correspondence with S. Dillon Ripley and Philip C. Ritterbush is notable in this regard.
  There are numerous letters written by Hutchinson to his family. Those from the Yale North India Expedition are particularly vivid. To his parents, Arthur and Evaline Hutchinson, Hutchinson wrote of his travels, while to Grace Pickford in New Haven, he sent more scientific and expedition details, as well as discussions of their private life. These letters contain verbal descriptions of photographs found in Series V. A large file of fragmentary letters written during the expedition is filed with the unidentified correspondence at the end of the series. There is a large correspondence with Hutchinson's sister Dorothea who lived with Hutchinson's mother. Occasionally both mother and sister wrote joint letters, and these are filed with the correspondence of Dorthea.
  During World War II, Hutchinson and his wife welcomed to their home Yemaiel Oved, the young daughter of his friend Gwendolyn Hughes, to protect her from the bombing taking place over England. The personal correspondence of Hughes and Oved is interesting in this regard. Yemaiel was like a child the Hutchinsons never had, and she maintained contact as she married, changed her name to Aris, and began raising her own family.
  - A, A unidentified, 1927-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 9)
  - Aaboe, Asger, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Academic Press Inc., 1944-1953, 1978, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, 1948-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 12 - 14)
    General
    See also: Series I, folders 325-326
  - Adey, Walter H., 1979-1980, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ahrens, Louis H., 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Aldrich, Henry R. (Box 18, Folder 309)
    See also: Series I, folder 309
  - Alexander, George L., 1948-1949, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Allee, W. C., 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Allen, Ruth, 1970-1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1949-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1944-1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    See also: Series I, folder 784
  - American Geophysical Society. Lakes Committee, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences, 1949-1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - American Journal of Science, 1940-1957, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - American Museum of Natural History, 1945-1959, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 25 - 26)
    See also: Series I, folder 834
  - American Naturalist, 1950-1953, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1937, 1954-1971, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - American Scientist, 1956-1988 (Box 2, Folder 29 - 32)
  - American Society of Limnology and Oceanography, 1939, 1945-1956, 1970-1987 (Box 2, Folder 33 - 39)
  - American Society of Naturalists, 1950-1958, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - American-Soviet Science Society, 1944-1948 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - American Statistical Association, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - American Trust for the British Library, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Anderson, Myrdene, 1970-1988 (Box 3, Folder 44 - 52)
  - Applewhite, Philip, 1971-1978 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Arber, Muriel, 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Archiv für Hydrobiologia, 1941, 1959-1966 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Aris, Yemaiel, 1979-1990 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    See also: Series I, folder 637
  - Aschenbach, Anna, 1979-1991 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Ashmole, N. Philip, 1958-1971 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Avery, George (Box 49, Folder 813)
    See also: Series I, folder 813
  - Avila, Enrigue, 1946-1958 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Ayala, Francisco J., 1976-1990 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Ba-Bo, 1922-1991 (Box 4, Folder 61 - 65)
  - Br-By, 1921-1988 (Box 5, Folder 66 - 68)
  - Baas Becking, L. G. M., 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Bache Fund, 1937-1944 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Bailes, Kendall, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Baitsell, George A., 1941-1977 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Baity, Elizabeth Chesley, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Baldi, Edgaro, 1946-1951 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Bannister, F. A., 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Barcroft, Henry, 1954, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Bateson, Gregory, 1939-1968 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Bateson, Mary Catherine, 1970, 1981-1987 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Baudisch, Oskar, 1943-1947 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Becker, Dusty, 1984-1988 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Beddall, Barbara, 1963-1988 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Bennoit, Richard J., 1951-1987 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Berkshire-Litchfield Environmental Conservancy Council, Inc., 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Bevan, Arthur (Box 34, Folder 571)
    See also: Series I, folder 571
  - Bingham, Susan, undated (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Biological Abstracts, 1934, 1951-1953 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Biological Bulletin, 1951-1983 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - BioScience, 1971-1982 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Bishop, Allison (Box 26, Folder 414)
    See also: Series I, folder 414
  - Blumer, Karen, 1977-1990 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Bonatti, Enrico, 1959-1970 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Bond, Richard M., 1941, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Bormann, F. Herbert, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Borowsky, Richard L., 1967-1986 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Boston University, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Botkin, Daniel B., 1981 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Bowen, Jean, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Bowen, Vaughan T., 1942-1948, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Bowmaker, Alan Philip MacGowan, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Bradley, Wilmot H., 1936-1978 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Braithwaite, Margaret Masterman, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Brewer, Derek, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Brewer, George E., Jr., 1948-1957 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Brewster, Kingman, 1962-1986 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Brinck, Per, 1943-1978 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - British Museum, 1934-1990 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - British Phosphate Commissioners, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Broadus, James, 1984-1987 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1947-1953 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Brooks, Harvey, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Brooks, John L., 1945-1950, 1970-1973, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Brower, Jane Z., 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Brower, Lincoln P., 1952, 1959-1973, 1981-1985 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Brown, Harrison, 1949-1953 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Brugam, Richard, 1974-1979 (Box 7, Folder 113 - 114)
  - Bryce, David, 1928-1930 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Buettner-Janusch, John, 1963-1981 (Box 7, Folder 116 - 117)
  - Burch, William R., Jr., 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Buss, Leo, 1974-1991 (Box 7, Folder 119 - 121)
  - Butler, E. A., 1918-1925 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Ca-Ci, 1925-1987 (Box 7, Folder 123 - 126)
  - Cl-Cz, 1935-1991 (Box 8, Folder 127 - 132)
  - Cadwalader, Charles M. B. (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    See also: Series I, folders 12-14
  - Cairns, John, Jr., 1969-1989 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Calhoun, David W., 1948-1952 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - Campaign for Yale, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 135)
  - Caspari, Ernst W., 1949-1985 (Box 8, Folder 136)
  - Casteras, Susan, 1977-1986 (Box 8, Folder 137)
    See also: Series II, folder 4
  - Caswell, Hal, 1977, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - Center for Law and Social Policy, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 139 - 140)
  - Charnov, Eric, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Chenery, E. M., 1945-1950, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Chew, Frances S., 1973-1982, undated (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Childs, George H., 1950 (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - Church, Phil E. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    See also: Series I, folder 22
  - CIBA, 1947, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Clarke, George L., 1937-1952 (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - Cloos, Ernst (Box 39, Folder 609-610)
    See also: Series I, folder 609-610
  - Cloud, Preston E., Jr., 1953-1983 (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - Cobb, Boughton and Edith, 1952-1969, undated (Box 9, Folder 148)
  - Cody, Martin L., 1971-1976 (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - Cohen, Joel E., 1971-1988 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Coker, R. E., 1946-1950, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - Colinvaux, Paul A., 1961-1971, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 152 - 153)
  - Collins, Francis W., 1944-1959, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - Columbia Broadcasting System, 1947-1948 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - Conklin, Hal, 1968-1984 (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1942, 1946, 1975-1988 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 1949-1956 (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Connecticut Geological and Natural History Survey, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 159 - 160)
  - Connor, Valerie M., 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 161 - 162)
  - Conservation Foundation, 1941-1973 (Box 10, Folder 163 - 167)
    See also: Series I, box 6, folder 101
  - Conway, Edward J., 1944-1946 (Box 10, Folder 168)
  - Cook, Pamela and Robert, 1972-1982 (Box 10, Folder 169 - 170)
  - Cook, S. F., 1946-1947 (Box 10, Folder 171)
  - Coolidge, Harold, 1946-1947 (Box 10, Folder 172)
  - Cornell University Press, 1966-1980 (Box 10, Folder 173)
  - Covich, Alan, 1968-1981, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 174 - 176)
  - Cowgill, Ursula M., 1965-1990 (Box 10, Folder 177 - 180)
  - Cox, David, 1976-1981 (Box 11, Folder 181)
  - Cutler, Carl C., 1945 (Box 11, Folder 182)
  - D, 1920-1992, undated (Box 11, Folder 183 - 189)
  - D'Abramo, Louis C., 1980-1982 (Box 11, Folder 190)
  - Das, S. M., 1971-1973, 1980-1982 (Box 11, Folder 191)
  - Deevey, Edward S., 1937-1988, undated (Box 11, Folder 192 - 196)
    See also: Series II, folder 51